# 山东·济南
Jinan. Shandong
# 烧饼夹牛肉
Shaobing(baked, layered flatbread) with beef
# 济南四月的清晨 还是有些清冷的
It’s still a little bit cold in the early morning in April of Jinan
# 这样的温度 适合吃个有能量的早餐
It’s time to eat an energy breakfast under temperature like this
# 今天雪鱼来到回民街
Xue yu come to Muslim street today
# 咱尝一尝这边的烧饼夹牛肉
Let’s try Shaobing with beef
# 大姐 这个多少钱一个
Old sis, how much is it?
# 10块钱
10 yuan
# 拿两个就行
I want two Shaobing with beef
# 大哥 是刚才面已经揉完了 卖完了吗
Brother, is it sold out because you finish knead the dough?
# 卖完了
Yes, it is
# 一天就卖这么一缸面是吧   对对
Only sell a vat of dough every day? right
# 你看 像揉面 剁牛肉都是大哥自己来
Brother do the work of knead dough and chop beef by him own
# 而像烤烧饼都是让大姐来上
And big sis do the work of bake
# 两个人分工真的是很明确
The division of their work between them is clear
# 先炕再烤
Fry it before roast
# 上面是不抹油的（会用油擦一下铁板）
There is not a lot oil on the big pan (they will smear some oil on the big pan)
# 看我们买的10块钱一个的牛肉夹馍
Look the shaobing with beef
# 肉都要冒出来了
Beef is about coming out
# 在寒冷的清晨 看着冒着热气的牛肉
Look at the beef with hot air in the cold early morning
# 真的是特别舒服
Pretty comfortable
# 芝麻还好多
With plenty sesames
# 这么闻着就是 面香味和牛肉的香味特别浓郁
Very strong smells of shaobing and beef when you smell it
# 我要先吃一口了
I’m going to have one bite
# 好咸啊
Very salty
# 牛肉 汤汁特别多
juicy beef
# 咬一口不会觉得噎着
It won’t choke you with one bite of beef
# 牛肉是五香的 酱香的
The beef is five spiced favor
# 把它剁成细末 细丝夹在烧饼里
Minced beef in shaobing
# 烧饼夹牛肉 分量这么重
With huge amount
# 我觉得不仅我能吃饱
I think not only me can get full
# 像一个大汉 也能吃得饱的
A strong man gets full too
# 现在快7点了 后面的烧饼夹牛肉忙碌起来了
It’s about 7 am and they start get busy now
# 大姐 牛肉烧饼作为早餐 顾客一般都买几个
Big sis, how many shaobing with beef customers buy as their breakfast as usual?
# 这个不一定
It depends
# 买最多的时候 有的人一买二三十个 十来个 这情况每天都有
Someone buy twenty or thirsty shaobing with beef at most, it happens everyday
# 因为他们都知道这是用的鲜牛肉 现宰的活牛
Because they knew that it made by fresh beef, freshly slaughtered cattle
# 进口的和我这牛肉相差15块钱吧
Imports beef is cost 15 yuan more than my beef
# 现在我买的牛肉32块钱一斤
Now my beef is 32 yuan every catty
# 平时买36块钱一斤
36 yuan every catty as regularly
# 这个就是 一般来说
usually
# 你要是长期在这个地方能干下去
If you want work here in a long time
# 就必须得讲诚信 必须讲质量 必须讲味道
You must be integrity with good quality and good favor
# 因为现在人花钱他就是说
Because now customer pay their money for quality of food
# 你再深的巷子 只要味道好 他也愿意来
He will come and eat even if the place is far and hard to looking for
# 大姐早上8点收摊
Big sis close their stall at 8 am
# 下午4点 山东济南
4 pm. Jinan. Shandong
# 大叔 猪头肉多少钱了
Uncle, how much for pig’s head meat
# 38元一斤
38 yuan for every catty
# 行 20块钱的猪头肉
Okay, I want 20 yuan of pig’s head meat
# 我给你称
I weight it
# 来 少来点吧
Okay, less of it
# 行 好好好
okay
# 这都没有了 卖完了
All sold out
# 不是4点开始营业吗
Isn’t it open at 4 pm?
# 3点半 他们都挨着号排队
They start line up at 3:30 pm
# 顾客：顺着这个味道就找来了
Customer: I come here for follow the smell
# 俺这老汤都多少年了吧 精华全在汤里的
You can see how old my soups are, the essence is all in the soup
# 都是您们两个人在这边干吗  是的
Only you two work here? yeah
# 对 这是猪头肉
Yeah, this is pork head meat
# 我先掀开你看看
Let me open for you to see it
# 猪头肉怎么卖的   38元一斤 但是都卖完了
How much for pig’s head meat? 38 yuan for every catty, but all sold out now
# 大叔一直吆喝着卖完了卖完了
Uncle keep shouting “sold out” “sold out”
# 开始干的时候还是小鲜肉
when the business start, he was young
# 现在成大叔级了
But now he become an uncle
# 一般几点出来
What time it open usually?
# 不到4点
Less than 4 pm
# 你要想买肠子 两点半就得来 想买大肠
Come at 2:30 if you want buy large intestine
# 不排个前三四名的买不上大肠
You need rank in the top three or four to buy large intestine
# 买大肠得两点半来吗
I need to come at 2:30 pm?
# 大肠做的少 买的人多
Less large intestine but a lot of people want it
# 如果不是2点半来  那也需要早来
You need come earlier
# 他不是四点出摊吗
Isn’t he open at 4 pm?
# 提前排队
Line up before it open
# 我说想吃肥肠 猪尾巴这些的必须早来
Come earlier if you want intestine or pig’s tail
# 这一共有多少种
How many types of neat over there?
# 生肉 250斤 20多种肉
250 catties of raw pork and more than 20 types of pork
# 来给我弄点肉汤
Get me some pork soup
# 这下好了 不仅肉得抢着买
Not only pork in rush to buy it
# 大家连汤都不放过
Same as pork soup as well
# 这个老汤回去怎么吃
What we eat with the old soup in home?
# 喝面条 吃米饭都行
With noodle and rice is fine
# 炖豆腐 炸豆腐
Stewed tofu and fried tofu
# 还有炒鸡蛋
And fried eggs
# 做卤肉确实累
It makes me tired to make pickled pork
# 早上3点就起床 你说的是实在话
Must get up at 3 am, be honestly
# 太累了 年轻人吃不了这个苦
Too tired, young people cannot suffer like us
# 虽然说 卖得快 但是背后累
Even it sold fast but behind it is suffer
# 你得去要货
You need to buy pork
# 要完货再清理
And clean it
# 再煮再炖出来 卤出来
Boil it before stewing it, and then pickle it
# 炖肉好弄 主要是收拾干净
Stew meat is easy, the point is clean it up
# 你看心了吗 都切开 把有血的地方收拾掉
You see the heart? Cut it and clean the blood
# 你看这耳朵是一个个都得烙猪毛
You see, you need to burn the hair of pork ear off
# 就是清理费事
It really takes time to clean it
# 这次咱们是买的20块钱的猪头肉还有10块钱的猪肝
We bought 20-yuan pig’s head meat and 10-yuan pork liver
# 可以看到这个小摊上 人特别多
You can notice there are lots of customers surround the stall
# 叔叔阿姨也很健谈
Uncle and aunt are also very talkative
# 这么一个小的摊 但是感觉到烟火气息特别浓重
Such a small booth but with street food feel
# 好多老顾客 其实也不仅是来买肉吃
Many old customers not only for buying pork
# 还有的时候 也顺带聊聊天
Also, they come for talking by the way
# 还有专程来要老汤 下面条 下米饭的
Someone coming for old soup to eat with noodle and rice
# 今天的这份猪头肉是偶遇到的
We are very lucky to have the last pig’s head meat
# 没想到 阿姨和叔叔这么健谈
Unexpectedly, aunt and uncle are so talkative
# 让我们整个的拍摄都充满了欢声笑语
Make our whole shooting with full of fun
# 我去的时候只剩了半匹猪头
There only half of pig’s head meat left when I come
# 我后面的人 就没有人再能够买到猪头肉了
People who are behind me not able to get pig’s head meat
# 我戴着口罩都能闻到猪头肉的香味
I can smell the smell of pig's head meat even if I’m wearing a mask
# 我们看一看 猪头肉到底有什么奇妙的地方
Let’s take a look how delicious the pig’s head meat is
# 能够让这么多的顾客 一直心心念念到
Why it makes so many customers miss
# 不过 叔叔这边没有给我们切
But uncle did not cut it for us
# 猪头肉 这边是瘦的 这边就是肥的
Pig’s head meat, this is lean, there is fatty
# 很明显
Very obviously
# 我觉得猪头肉 除了有点咸还是很不错的
I think pig’s head meat is pretty good except a little bit salty
# 肉 炖得软烂
Meat stewed very soft
# 就是嚼一嚼就能够咽得下去这一种
I can swallow it by chewing it a bit
# 我用手 轻轻地一掰
I use my hand and gently break it
# 不管是肥肉还是瘦肉 都很容易把它掰扯掉
it’s easy to pull it off Whether it’s fat or lean
# 看到肉的纹理了吗
See the texture of pork
# 这个肉不用吃就会很香
????????????
# 刚才师傅说嘛 很多人都是闻着味就过来了
Uncle said that many customers following the smell
# 吃猪头肉 一定要肥瘦搭配
Eat pig’s head meat must be fatty and lean
# 瘦的呢 就是这种咸香味十足
Lean meat is salty and fragment
# 带点肥的呢 又嫩 又有汤汁
Fatty is soft and juicy
# 两个搭配在一起 就是极好的
It’s a good combo to put fatty and lean together
# 我感觉在吃肉的时候 很多人在注视着我
I feel people stared me when I’m eating
# 我是全场的焦点
I am the focus of the crowd